Guide to the Lewis Rubenstein Papers, approximately 1950-1974
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Lewis Rubenstein Papers
approximately 1950-1974
Rubenstein, Lewis W. (Lewis William), 1908-
2 cubic feet (5 boxes, 1 OV folder)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Sketches of faculty members and campus scenes and sketchbooks produced throughout Rubenstein's career at Vassar, and two copies of his film "Time Painting."
Biographical Note
Lewis Rubenstein was born in 1908 in Buffalo, NY, the son of Emil and Hannah (Hirshman) Rubenstein. In 1930 he graduated from Harvard University with a B.A. in Fine Arts. He then spent two years as a Harvard Travelling Fellow in Europe, studying in France and Italy. From 1935 to 1938 he accepted commissions to paint frescoes murals in Harvard museums, as well as buildings in Detroit. In 1937 he began his long career as an art educator, joining the faculty of Vassar in 1939 as Instructor in Art. After a year's leave of absence to paint another commission, Rubenstein returned to Vassar in 1941. In 1942 he married Erica Beckh and took another leave of absence from Vassar to paint ship camouflage for the U.S. Navy during the Second World War. In 1946 he returned to Vassar as an Assistant Professor of Art. He became Associate Professor in 1951 and remained at the college until his retirement in 1974. As an artist, Rubenstein worked in a variety of media, from oil paint to "water-based techniques" such as ink, fresco, and watercolor (see "Introduction," Lewis Rubenstein: Retrospective Exhibition). He also continued to draw and sketch, producing during a series of sketched portraits of Vassar colleagues during faculty meetings. Rubenstein exhibited his work widely in galleries such as Harvard's Busch-Reisinger Museum, the Albany Institute of History and Art, the National Academy of Design, and the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York. Lewis Rubenstein died in June 2003 at age 94 in Shelborne, Vermont.
Scope and Content Note
Sketches of faculty members and campus scenes and sketchbooks produced throughout Rubenstein's career at Vassar, and two copies of his film "Time Painting."
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the
Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
Portraits, American
Organizations:
Vassar College--Buildings; Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College--Students
Document Types:
Sketches; Sketchbooks; Film (material by form)
VCL Categories:
Art and Artists; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, November 2011. Updated January 2012. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, August 2023.
Acquisition Information
Original Acquisition date unknown.
Series List
- Series I. Vassar Sketches, circa 1950-1974
  Framed sketches of faculty members and scenes of College life.
  Arranged alphabetically.
- Series II. Assorted Sketches and Sketchbooks, 1950-1971
  Bound sketchbooks and assorted loose sketches, some of which are studies for the finished sketches in Series I.
- Series III. Films, circa 1968-1972
  Two prints of the film "Time Painting."
  Arranged chronologically.
Container List
- Series I. Vassar Sketches
  - "Campus Fantasy,", undated (Box 5)
  - Chatterton, C. K., undated (Box 1)
  - Christie, John (1), undated (Box 3)
  - Christie, John (2), undated (Box 3)
  - Constantinople, Anne, undated (Box 4)
  - Darlington, Beth, undated (Box 2)
  - Drouilhet, Elizabeth, undated (Box 1)
  - Drouilhet, Elizabeth, undated (Box 2)
  - Fahlund, G. Gregory, undated (Box 2)
  - Fortna, Robert T., undated (Box 3)
  - "Four Runners,", undated (Box 4)
  - Gittleman, Anne and Elizabeth Drouilhet, undated (Box 4)
  - "Graduation,", undated (Box 5)
  - Gutman, Helmut (?), undated (Box 1)
  - Havelock, Christine, undated (Box 3)
  - Johnsen, John, undated (Box 3)
  - Johnson, Glen (?), undated (Box 2)
  - Krautheimer, Richard and Oliver Tonks, undated (Box 4)
  - Mace, Dean, undated (Box 2)
  - "The Open Hour,", undated (Oversize Multi-Collection Box)
  - "Problems of Early Marriage,", undated (Box 5)
  - Rappaport, Rhoda, undated (Box 3)
  - Regnier, Jerome (?), undated (Box 2)
  - Richardson, Frances and Kathleen, undated (Box 2)
  - Rittenkamp, James, undated (Box 2)
  - Schalk, David, undated (Box 3)
  - Simpson, Alan (1), undated (Box 1)
  - Simpson, Alan (2), undated (Box 3)
  - Simpson, Alan (3), undated (Box 3)
  - Stillman, Peter, undated (Box 3)
  - Stone, Joseph, undated (Box 2)
  - "Students on Campus,", undated (Box 1)
  - Tait, Marion, undated (Box 3)
  - Timm, Ruth, undated (Box 2)
  - Tokay, Elbert, undated (Box 3)
  - Tokay, Elbert and unidentified woman, undated (Box 3)
  - "Two Young Ladies With Racquets,", undated (Box 4)
  - "Vassar Venus,", undated (Box 4)
  - Weingartner, Rudolph, undated (Box 3)
  - Wells, Barbara, undated (Box 2)
- Series II. Assorted Sketches and Sketchbooks
  - Assorted Sketches, undated (Folder 4.1)
  - Assorted Sketches, undated (Folder 4.2)
  - Sketchbook, 1950 (Folder 1.1)
  - Sketchbook, 1950; [photocopy] (Folder 4.3)
  - Sketchbook, 1965 (Folder 4.4)
  - Sketchbook, 1971 (Folder 1.1)
- Series III. Films
  - "Time Painting,", circa 1968 (Reel 1)
  - "Time Painting,", 1972 (Reel 2)